A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Office Files of Sir Brian Urquhart FA550
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Office Files of Sir Brian Urquhart
1986-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA550
13.6 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in 8 series by file type.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, meeting records, documentation of writing and regional projects, speaking engagements and events, and united nations studies.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, >Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Sketch - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
The Ford Foundation’s expansion era (1950-1965) began when the Gaither Study Committee Report placed “peace” as the area of top priority for the Foundation and set the Ford Foundation on a global course. Board Chair Henry Ford II writing in the 1951 Annual Report of the Foundation, identified “the danger of war” as the “the prime threat to human welfare today.” Under the leadership of the three Ford Foundation presidents in this period-- Paul Hoffman, H. Rowan Gaither and Henry Heald--and several key trustees, notably the two seriatim chairs, John J. McCloy and Julius A. Stratton, the Foundation programs were largely informed by the post-World War II desire to avoid nuclear war and promote greater understanding among the world’s peoples, strengthening of the United Nations, and enhancing both private and public American participation in world affairs. The strong board presence of university presidents and former leaders of postwar reconstruction efforts in Europe also helped to inform Ford’s approach to building the field of peace and international security in the United States and encouraged extensive overseas activities.
For example, the first three presidents of the expanded Foundation ranged from government and business leadership experience to academic and nonprofit: Paul Hoffman (at Ford, 1950-1953) ran the Marshall Plan in Europe; H. Rowan Gaither Staffer (1948-1953), President (1953-1956) and Trustee (1956-1958) had MIT and Rand experience; Henry Heald, former president, Illinois Institute of Technology and New York University, President (1956-1966). The trustees also ran the leadership gamut from government and nonprofits to academic: Trustee John J. McCloy (from 1953; chair, 1959-1965) was assistant Secretary of War during World War II and chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations; and Trustee Julius A. Stratton (Trustee from 1955; chair, 1966-1970) was president of MIT.
When Ford became an international foundation in 1950, it had a small staff and operated through separate funds. The expansive period in the 1950s and 1960s resulted in a large number of field offices, which increased Ford’s global footprint. Support focused on a mix of US university-based programs for research and training; think-tanks for policy-oriented meetings and policy research; and action projects specifically in less developed countries. The Foundation’s focus on peace, freedom, and democracy played out against the Cold War backdrop for scientific and military competition between the United States, the Soviet Union and China.
Under President Hoffman, the Foundation’s work was organized by the areas identified in the Gaither Committee Report: Area One, the Establishment of Peace; Area Two, The Strengthening of Democracy; Area Three, The Strengthening of the Economy; Area Four, Education in a Democratic Society; and Area Five, Individual Behavior and Human Relations.
Program differentiation began in the Gaither era. When he began in 1953, he introduced the following programs, with international work under nearly all of them: International Programs, Public Affairs Programs, Program in Economic Development and Administration (mainly U.S. based), Education Program, The TV-Radio Workshop, and Behavioral Sciences Program. In 1954, the Foundation gave prominence to the international work explicitly through changing the program names and separating international affairs and overseas development. The 1954 program names were: The Advancement of Education, Education for Democracy, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas, Economic Development and Administration, the Behavioral Sciences, and Overseas Development. In 1955, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas became Increasing International Understanding. In 1956, the last year of the Gaither presidency, the program roster read: Education in the United States, The Behavioral Sciences, Public Affairs, Hospital Aid (only in the U.S.), Economic Development and Administration, International Understanding, and Overseas Development. Names changed but the program focus often remained the same.
President Heald maintained the areas of international interest of Hoffman and Gaither. The International Affairs program housed the programs based in the United States, Europe and Japan, with a few activities linking American and developing countries institutions. The Overseas Training and Research Program took over the efforts to increase American understanding of international issues. From 1957-1959, an International Legal Studies program, run from New York, helped build law programs in developing countries. Starting in 1959, the Overseas Development program comprised all the regional and country offices. In fiscal year 1964, Heald convinced the trustees to add a new focus on population, with grants both in the United States and overseas.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Summary - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
With the ever-increasing budget and trustee willingness to invade capital, presidents Hoffman, Gaither and Heald oversaw vast growth in the Foundation's international activities in the United States, other developed countries and developing countries. Activities crossed disciplines, institutions, and national boundaries, although few crossed intra-foundation boundaries. Under the three presidents, Foundation staff in various domestic and international offices from New York interacted with the regional and country offices headed by representatives. Usually in this period, however, these offices in fact worked more closely with local governments than with New York staff, reinforcing the commitment to locally led social and economic development in less-developed countries.
The shared values of this early period reflected as much the continuing competition between the Communist and capitalist worlds as the concerns about maintaining peace. The Cold War provided the contextual continuity for grantmaking on the core themes of increasing American understanding of the rest of the world, building and strengthening connections not only with European and Asian democracies but also with Eastern European countries, the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba.
- Chronological Correspondence, 1986-1995; I
  - Chrons, Feb-Mar 1986 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1986 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jun-Sep 1986 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1986 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1987 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1987 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1987 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1987 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1988 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1988 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1988 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1988 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1989 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1989 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1989 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1989 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1990 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1990 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1990 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1990 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1991 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1991 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1991 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1991 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1992 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1992 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1992 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1992 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jan-Feb 1993 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Mar 1993 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1993 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1993 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1993 (Box 2)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1994 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1994 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1994 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1994 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, Jan-Mar 1995 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, Apr-Jun 1995 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, Jul-Sep 1995 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, Oct-Dec 1995 (Box 3)
- Meetings, 1986-1995; II
  - Palme Commission -- New Delhi, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Palme Commission, 1986-1993 (Box 4)
  - UNA/UN Panel, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Olaf Palme's Funeral -- Stockholm, Mar 15-16, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Ditchley, Mar 21-23, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Ralphe Bunche Conference, May 5-6, 1986 (Box 4)
  - UNA Panel, May 9-10, 1986 (Box 4)
  - UNIFIL Workshop -- Oslo, Jul 1-4, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Keswick/Strathclyde, May 19-21, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Honorary Degree -- Keele University, Jun 29-Jul 3, 1987 (Box 4)
  - UNA Panel Lunch, Sep 16, 1987 (Box 4)
  - BBC Radio Program, Sep 1987 (Box 4)
  - Carter Center Mediation, Nov 4-5, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Carter Center -- Middle East Conference, Nov 16-18, 1987 (Box 4)
  - South Africa/Carter Center, Mar 30-31, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Ditchley, Jun 17-19, 1988 (Box 4)
  - BBC, Jun 20, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Brioni, Jul 17-22, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Martin Wight Memoral Lecture -- London -- Chatham House, Sep 27, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Berlin-Leiden, Nov 20-22, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Oslo, Dec 11-16, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Stockholm, Jan 10-11, 1989 (Box 4)
  - San Diego, Feb 1-2, 1989 (Box 4)
  - York University -- Toronto, Mar 2, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Middle East Development Conference, Mar 23-26, 1989 (Box 4)
  - John Bright Lecture -- London, Mar 28, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Ditchley, May 5-7, 1989 (Box 4)
  - IPA -- Briarcliff Manor, Sep 19, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Copenhagen -- Lund, Oct 15-18, 1989 (Box 4)
  - IEWSS -- Frankfurt, Oct 19-21, 1989 (Box 4)
  - International Affairs Program -- Cairo/Jerusalem, Oct 23-27, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Study Group -- Gorbachev/UN Reform -- Franck: NYU Law School, Jan-Apr 1990 (Box 4)
  - IEWSS Annual Conference -- Stockholm, Jun 7-9, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Fletcher School Symposium -- Defining a New World Order, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Birenbaum -- Reinventing the United Nations, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Pearson Center, Apr 24-25, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Keystone, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Quebec, Apr 6-7, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Canada -- Rapid Deployment, 1995 (Box 4)
- Speaking Engagements, 1986-1995; III
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1995 (Box 5)
- Subject Files, 1987-1995; IV
  - Aborted BBC Project, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Ralph Bunche Film (1/3), 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Ralph Bunche Film (2/3), 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Ralph Bunche Film (3/3), 1993 (Box 5)
  - Disaster Relief, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Iran-Iraq War Project, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Otunnu Project, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Secretary General Good Offices, 1993 (Box 5)
  - TV Projects, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - United Nations TV Project, 1994 (Box 5)
- Writing Projects, V
  - Articles, Reviews, Op-Ed Pieces, Lectures, 1986-1989 (Box 6)
  - Articles, Reviews, Op-Ed Pieces, Reviews, Pamphlets (1/2), 1990-1995 (Box 6)
  - Articles, Reviews, Quotes, Prefaces, Introductions, etc. (2/2), 1990-1995 (Box 6)
  - Bunche Materials -- Ford Foundation -- Box Sheets, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Study -- Distribution, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Study -- Report Release, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Study -- "A World in Need of Leadership", 1991 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Studies -- Leadership -- Ambassador's Meeting, Nov 20, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Preliminary Letter, Jan 26, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Responses to 1/26/90 Letter, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Questionaires/Responses, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Leadership Project, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Project Meeting -- Uppsala -- New York -- Agenda and Attendance, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Project Meeting -- Uppsala -- New York -- 4/24 Meeting, Apr 24, 1990 (Box 7)
  - United Nations -- Emergencies Project -- Correspondence, 1991 (Box 7)
  - United Nations Secretariat Reorganization Project, 1991 (Box 7)
- Regional Files, VI
  - Africa, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - Cambodia, 1989-1992 (Box 7)
  - Impact of East-West Tensions on the Third World, 1986-1987 (Box 7)
  - Middle East (1/2), 1986-1991 (Box 7)
  - Middle East (2/2), 1989-1995 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1986-1995; VII
  - Ford Foundation -- General (1/2), 1986-1994 (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation -- General (2/2), 1986-1995 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1987 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1987 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1988 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1988 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1989 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1989 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1990 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1990 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1991 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1991 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1992 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1992 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1993 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1993 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1994 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1994 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jan-Jun 1995 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Jul-Dec 1995 (Box 8)
- United Nations Studies, 1986-1995; VIII
  - United Nations Current File, 1986-1992 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Dinner, Apr 21-22, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Notes and Follow-up, Apr 21-22, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Agenda and [illegible], Apr 21-22, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Invitations and Replies, Apr 21-22, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting I -- Proceedings and Follow-up, Jul 15, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting I -- Invitations and Acceptances, Jul 15, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting II -- Papers, Dec 7, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting II -- Notes, Dec 7, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting II -- Invite Letter and Follow-up`, Dec 7, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Invitations and Acceptances, Jul 11, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Agenda and Attendance, Jul 11, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Pike Paper, Jul 11, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Cambodia Notes, Jul 11, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Multilateral Challenges, Nov 20, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Maintenance of International Peace and Security -- More Ad Hoc Measures or a System?, May 30, 1990 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Prevention and Limitation of Conflict Through Multilateral Means, Jun 5, 1990 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Global Environmental Change and the Evolution of the United Nations System, Jul 11, 1990 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Leadership for the Future I, Nov 20, 1990 (Box 9)
  - United Nations Ford Foundation Grants, 1991-1993 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- United Nations Leadership for the Future II, Jan 30, 1991 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- United Nations Leadership for the Future III, Mar 14, 1991 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- The Gulf Crisis -- The Security Council and the Future, May 9, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Advisory Group on United Nations Financing, 1992 (Box 10)
  - United Nations System Study, 1992-1995 (Box 10)
  - Strengthening United Nations Capacity for Preventative Diplomacy, Peace-making and Peacekeeping, Apr 7, 1992 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Group First Meeting, Sep 16, 1992 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Group Second Meeting, Oct 30, 1992 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Congress -- Volker Mailing, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Press Articles on Report, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Meeting, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Background Papers, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Costs of Project, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Peace-Keeping Training, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- UN, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Advisory Group, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Volcker and Ogata, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Frank Thomas Memoranda and Talking Points, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Other, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Financing Project Office Memoranda, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Group Comments on Final Report, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Transmittal/Response/Requests, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Requests for Report, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group Third Meeting, Jan 25, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- United Nations Financing Repair, May 6, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Yale Group -- United Nation's Next Fifty Years, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
  - United Nations Volunteer Force, 1995 (Box 11)